Half Century Records, 1976-1981
University of Houston Libraries
Half Century Records
1976-1981
University of Houston. Office of University Relations
On December 7, 1976 President Philip G. Hoffman announced the 50th Anniversary of the University, with events to run throughout 1977. This collection consists of documents relating to the various events of the celebration and the committee overseeing the events. Materials include agendas, correspondence, minutes, brochures, forms, calendars, commemorative newspaper articles, and press clippings dating primarily from 1976 and 1977.
3 boxes; 3 linear feet
1984-001
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Event History
In December 1976, President Philip Hoffman began a project that he was particularly determined to bring to a successful conclusion. On December 7, at the Houston Country Club, he announced the 50th Anniversary of the University, with events to run throughout 1977. At that kickoff event, Hoffman also announced the UH 50 Fund, a fundraising campaign with the goal of raising between $23.5 and $32.5 million for priority needs by 1981. During this period the Cullen Foundation pledged $3 million to endow nine distinguished professorships contingent upon the university raising another $6 million in matching funds. The university selected four topical areas for the yearlong celebration: resources, technologies, lifestyles, and environments. These topics were interwoven in lectures and seminars throughout the year.
The events of the half-century observance were varied and included: the French government sending an arts festival; a series of noted speakers, seminars, and conferences; a German Expressionist art exhibition and lectures; a symposium in conjunction with the dedication of the new College of Optometry; and the dedication of the Freeman Wing of the library.
Scope and Contents
The UH Half Century Records arrived at the archives in relatively good order, which has been maintained where possible. The collection consists mainly of documents relating to the various events of the celebration and the committee overseeing the events. Materials include agendas, correspondence, minutes, brochures, forms, calendars, commemorative newspaper articles, and press clippings. The collection dates almost entirely from 1976-1977, with a few items from as late as 1981. The materials are organized into six series: Planning and Preparation; Half Century Events; Media; Personnel; Commemorative Materials; and Afterwards.
Acquisition
Transfer from the Office of University Relations, 1984.
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Index Terms
Terms are either Library of Congress Subject Headings or taken from local sources.
Subjects
University of Houston History; University of Houston Administration
Subjects(Persons)
Hoffman, Phillip G.
Subjects (Organizations)
University of Houston; University of Houston. Office of University Relations.
Formats
Correspondence; Minutes; Agendas; Brochures; Clippings
Detailed Description
- Planning and Preparation (Box 1, Folder 1-40)
  This series contains forty folders dating from 1976 to 1978. Whenever possible the original order has been maintained, although some changes have been made to facilitate access. This series has been organized into four sub-series: General Planning, Half Century Brochure, Half Century Forms, and Half Century Logo Use. The folders contain minutes, brochures, mailing lists, meeting notes, programs and invitations, and drafts of various brochures.
  - General Planning (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
    This sub-series consists of twelve folders arranged alphabetically. The Planning Committee folders are arranged first by date, then alphabetically. Materials include meeting notes, planning strategies, campaign objectives, and other similar materials needed to launch the celebration. Dr. Patricia Teed served as Director of the Half-Century Program.
    - Half Century - Meetings with Hoffman, August 1976-June 1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Planning Committee - Agendas and Notices, August-September 1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Planning Committee - Correspondence, August-September 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Planning Committee - Meeting Notes (Teed), August-September 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Planning Committee - Final Report, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Planning Committee - Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Planning Committee - Membership Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Planning Committee - Planning Matrices, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Planning Correspondence with Deans, April-September 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Program Planning Notes - Teed, July 8-September 20, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Promotional Proposals, November 22, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Proposals Re Semi-Centennial, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Half Century Brochure (Box 1, Folder 13-18)
    This sub-series consists of six folders relating to the creation of a special Half-Century brochure. Folders are arranged in the order in which they were received with items for the creation of the brochure followed by folders related to the mailing of the brochure, and finally the brochure itself. Materials include printing quotations, working drafts of brochure text, mailing lists of individuals, and copies of the final brochure.
    - General, November 1976-March 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - General, November 1976-March 1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Mailing Lists Submitted by Departments, May 3-24, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Master Mailing Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Brochure, April-November 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Brochure, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Half Century Forms (Box 1, Folder 19-31)
    There are thirteen folders in this sub-series, arranged alphabetically. Most of the forms in this series are single page documents probably used to gather information on individuals and colleges for use in press releases or newspapers articles covering the yearlong celebration. Other forms are simple departmental forms used for various purposes like tracking long distance telephone calls, weekly part-time staff reports, and forms used to track different celebration events.
    - Assignment Sheet, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - College Information Forms, September 8, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Departmental Update (Part I and II), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Distinguished Professorship Forms, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Event Sheet, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Form Letter (turn down for funding), undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Half Century Matrices, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Long-distance Call Report, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Notice of Confirmed Event, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Notification of Planned Event, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Part-time Employee Weekly Report, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Social Event Sheet, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Speaker Sheet, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Half Century Logo Use (Box 1, Folder 32-40)
    This sub-series contains nine folders, arranged alphabetically. The folders contain examples of different brochures that used the Half-Century Logo, announcements of guest speakers, press clippings pertaining to the new logo, and various examples of the logo itself.
    - Brochures, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Brochures, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - General/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Lecture Announcements, January-November 1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Logo Sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Mechanical for Fliers, March 14, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Notes and Press, July 1976-November 1978 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Programs and Invitations, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Publications, 1976-Fall 1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Half Century Events (Box 1-3)
  This series is the largest with sixty-six folders dating from 1976 to 1978 and is arranged chronologically by event. Calendars for the year and general correspondence relating to Half Century events precede materials associated with specific events. Whenever possible the original order has been maintained. Folders contain materials relating to the many different events that took place before and during the yearlong celebration. Materials include correspondence, programs, invitations, fliers, and newspaper articles and they cover all events including the Half-Century Convocation and guest speakers like Buckminster Fuller and Richard Leaky.
  - General (Box 1, Folder 41-48)
    - Half Century Commencement, January-October 1977 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Half Century Program Calendars, October 1976-December 1977 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Half Century Monthly Academic Calendars, January-December 1977 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Programs Office Correspondence, July-December 1976 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Programs Office Correspondence, January-March 1977 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Programs Office Correspondence, April-October 1977 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Programs Office Correspondence, January-December 1977 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Half Century Student Festival, October 1976-November 1979 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Kickoff (Box 1, Folder 49-52)
    - Announcement by Philip Hoffman, November-December 1976 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Excellence Dinner, November-December 1976 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Press, December 1976-January 1977 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Cotton Bowl Game, December 1976-January 1977 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - French Contemporary Arts Festival (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
    - Chicago, Washington, D.C., October 1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, November 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Mailing List for French Festival, November 1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Materials Distributed to Visitors, November 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Newspaper Clippings and Publicity, November 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Schedules and Drafts, November 1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Teed-Planning, Meetings, October 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Fuller and Passive Design (Box 2, Folder 8-14)
    - Breakfast honoring Fuller, December 1976-January 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Dinner honoring Fuller, January 10-11, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Fliers and Brochures, January 10-12, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Notes and Memoranda, September 1976-June 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Fuller Biography and Photographs, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Passive Design Workshop, December 1976-January 1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Press, December 1976-May 1977 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Richard Leakey (Box 2, Folder 15-19)
    - Biographical Info, June 1973-December 1976 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Dinner and Luncheon Honoring, March 7-8, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Fliers, March 11, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Notes and Memoranda, March 1977 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Press and Newspaper, March 1977-October 1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - June Health Event (Box 2, Folder 20-24)
    - General, November 1976-May 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Sunday 6/26/77, February 25, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Slide Presentation, March 15-31, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - 6/27/77 Dinner, March-July 1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Symposia, June 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Half Century Convocation Committee (Box 2, Folder 25-31)
    - Agendas and Notices, March 15-April 25, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Minutes, March 15-May 3, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Notes and Correspondence. (Teed), March 1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Final Report, September 5-19, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Steering Committee, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Matrices, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Members, List of, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Half Century Convocation Events (Box 2-3)
    - Opera Studio Recital, February 1976-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - General/Notes/Planning, December 1976-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Academic Convocation, May-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Commemorative Newspapers, Summer-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Commemorative Newspapers, Summer-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Guests and Invitation Lists, July-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Bentsen, Senator Lloyd M., July-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Commager, Dr. Henry Steele, August-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Penn State Game (closed-circuit), August-September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - UCLA Game, September 12-13, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Maps (Access and general campus), September 17, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Programs, Invitations, Fliers, September 18, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Birthday Party/UC, September 8-19, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Schedules of Activities, September 9-19, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Press Strategy, September 1977 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Press, September-October 1977 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Open Houses, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Commager's Speech (Copies), September 1977-May 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Announcement (Press), undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Frank Press and Engineering Research Conference (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - Frank Press, August 1976-December 1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Engineering Research Conference, October 1976-November 1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Media `77 (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
    - Brochures and Graphics, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - General, March 1977-November 1981 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Press, March 1977-June 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Dinner, November 19, 1977, June 1977-November 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ian Richardson and Mental Health Symposium (Box 3, Folder 10-14)
    - Mental Health Symposium, September 2-October 28, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Richardson and Mental Health Press, November 29-December 12, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Richardson and Mental Health Programs, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Ian Richardson, November 15-December 1, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Richardson and Mental Health Dinner, December 7, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Media (Box 3, Folder 15-30)
  This series contains sixteen folders dating from 1976 to 1981 and is organized into two sub-series: Half-Century Press/Publicity and Community Services Brochure. The folders contain various brochures, general press coverage, University of Houston press releases and notes used in planning some of the events. Some of the brochures in this series were probably used as examples for the design of the Official University Half-Century brochure.
  - Half Century Press/Publicity (Box 3, Folder 15-19)
    This sub-series contains five folders, arranged chronologically. The folders contain general information relating to members of the press that the university wanted to contact regarding the celebration. The materials also include various press clippings covering the celebration.
    - Public Relations Notes, June 30, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Campus Workshop, February 1976-March 1977 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Press Clippings, September 1976-November 1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Press Releases, February-June 1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Feature Ideas, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Community Services Brochure (Box 3, Folder 20-30)
    This sub-series consists of eleven folders that contain materials relating to the Community Services Brochure produced by the university during the Half-Century celebration. The purpose of the brochure was to give an overview of the various areas of interaction between the University of Houston and the community. The materials consist of correspondence relating to the brochure, working drafts, notes and other information used in the brochure's publication.
    - Community Service, July 1976-January 1977 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Materials from Deans, Feb. 8-March 9, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Community Service Brochure, March 18-29, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - DRAFTS, August-November 1977 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - DRAFTS, August-November 1977 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Incoming Requests for Mailing, December 5-15, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Use File, December 1977-January 1978 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Original Copy, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Kent's Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Teed Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - UH System, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Personnel (Box 3, Folder 31-33)
  This series consists of three folders of correspondence between various people, both university employees and those outside the university consisting of notes in the planning of events, the design of the Half-Century Brochure, and other related materials.
  - General, January 17, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Busse, Alvin R., September 1976-March 1977 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Notes on Programmatic Counsel, August 4-September 27, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Commemorative Materials (Box 3, Folder 34-39)
  This series consists of six folders of material relating to different commemorative items created to honor the half-century. Included are newspaper advertisements for the commemorative Dr. Pepper Bottle, a deck of commemorative playing cards, newspaper articles about the posters used to symbolize the four topics of the celebration, and interoffice materials relating to the aerial photograph of the campus used during the event.
  - Playing Cards, October 27, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Posters, November 1976-April 1977 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Posters, Aerial Photo for Faculty from Munitz, February 10-September 1977 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Dr. Pepper Bottle, August 30, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Commemorative Materials, July 1976-July 1980 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Commemorative Newspaper, September 1977 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Afterwards (Box 3, Folder 40-42)
  This series consists of three folders. These materials include the Half Century Final Report from the Deputy Coordinator, Division of External Relations, Patricia Teed, to Chancellor Barry Munitz outlining the many challenges experienced by the Half Century Committee during their eighteen months in existence. This series also contains correspondence and press coverage of the forty-foot long multi-panel display exhibited in prominent locations throughout Houston during the celebration and a blueprint of the Half-Century Monolith.
  - Half Century Final Report, March 21, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Half Century Panel Exhibit, August 1977-August 1979 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Half Century Monolith, October 1977 (Box 3, Folder 42)